<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>counting | MeelGroup</title>
    <link>https://meelgroup.github.io/tag/counting/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://meelgroup.github.io/tag/counting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>counting</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://meelgroup.github.io/images/icon_hu1dd832c4da814f17fe02e3737f0ae144_14882_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>counting</title>
      <link>https://meelgroup.github.io/tag/counting/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>NPAQ</title>
      <link>https://meelgroup.github.io/project/npaq/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://meelgroup.github.io/project/npaq/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Neural networks are increasingly employed in safety-critical domains. This has prompted interest in verifying or certifying logically encoded properties of neural networks. Prior work has largely focused on checking existential properties, wherein the goal is to check whether there exists any input that violates a given property of interest. However, neural network training is a stochastic process, and many questions arising in their analysis require probabilistic and quantitative reasoning, i.e., estimating how many inputs satisfy a given property. To this end, our paper proposes a novel and principled framework to quantitative verification of logical properties specified over neural networks. Our framework is the first to provide PAC-style soundness guarantees, in that its quantitative estimates are within a controllable and bounded error from the true count. We instantiate our algorithmic framework by building a prototype tool called NPAQ that enables checking rich properties over binarized neural networks. We show how emerging security analyses can utilize our framework in 3 applications: quantifying robustness to adversarial inputs, efficacy of trojan attacks, and fairness/bias of given neural networks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GANAK</title>
      <link>https://meelgroup.github.io/project/ganak/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://meelgroup.github.io/project/ganak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given a Boolean formula $F$, the problem of  model counting, also referred to as #SAT, seeks to compute the number of solutions of $F$. Model counting is a fundamental problem with a wide variety of applications ranging from planning, quantified information flow to probabilistic reasoning and the like. The modern #SAT solvers tend to be either based on static decomposition, dynamic decomposition, or a hybrid of the two. Despite dynamic decomposition based #SAT solvers sharing much of their architecture with SAT solvers, the core design and heuristics of dynamic decomposition-based #SAT solvers has remained constant for over a decade. In this paper, we revisit the architecture of the state-of-the-art dynamic decomposition-based #SAT tool, sharpSAT, and demonstrate that by introducing a new notion of probabilistic component caching and the usage of universal hashing for exact model counting along with the development of several new heuristics can lead to significant performance improvement over state-of-the-art model-counters. In particular, we develop GANAK, a new scalable probabilistic exact model counter that outperforms state-of-the-art exact and approximate model counters sharpSAT and ApproxMC3 respectively, both in terms of PAR-2 score and the number of instances solved. Furthermore, in our experiments, the model count returned by GANAK was equal to the exact model count for all the benchmarks. Finally, we observe that recently proposed preprocessing techniques for model counting benefit exact model counters while hurting the performance of approximate model counters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
